Gay liberation papers, 1970-1978
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Gay liberation papers, 1970-1978
AZ 349
This collection includes correspondence, clippings, tapes, periodicals, and other material concerning the gay liberation movement in Arizona and on the West Coast, and related issues.
Gay Liberation Arizona Desert, II
1.7 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
Gay Liberation Arizona Desert (GLAD II) was local affiliation of the national Gay Liberation Front. Their purpose in meeting was to educate the public and to raise the level of awareness about gays in the Tucson Community.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series:
Series I: GLAD II Historical Archives
Series II: Subject Resources
Series III: Articles authored by Jack Latham, 1973-1975
Series IV: Gay Sunshine Material
Series V: Audio Recordings, 1973-1975
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes correspondence, clippings, tapes, periodicals, and other material concerning the gay liberation movement in Arizona and on the West Coast, and related issues. Includes issues of the newspaper Gay Sunshine, 1970-1973.
Access Terms
Gay Sunshine
Homosexuality
Gay liberation movement -- Arizona
Gay liberation movement -- United States
Gay liberation movement -- Periodicals
Correspondence
Newspapers
Container List
- Series I: GLAD II Historical Archives
  - Guide to the collection. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - GLAD, ASU, Tempe, Arizona. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Clippings, newsletters, and memorabilia of the original GLAD organization in Tempe.
  - GLAD II, History and Purposes. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Memorabilia, a partial chronology, historical notes of the organization in Tucson; statements of purpose.
  - Glad II, Correspondence. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Both outgoing and incoming correspondence arranged chronologically. Additional letters in Box 1, 14 & 15.
  - General clippings. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Clippings from local news sources about GLAD II and the Tucson gay work; other clippings are in Box 1,14 & 15.
  - Advertisements. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Classified and display ads from The Arizona Daily Wildcat and The New Times regarding GLAD II and Tucson gay movement activities.
  - National Directories. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    These items were used by GLAD II for mailings and for referral information for transient gays.
  - Referral Materials. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    These materials were used in telephone referrals and/or provided to other agencies to use in dealing with gay clients; included here is a 1975 description by Samuel Albert of the referral and general services of Jack Latham and Dan Downey. Materials in Box 2 were more general sources of referral information.
  - Discussion Materials. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    This collection of articles were items frequently used by GLAD II in general meetings, consciousness-raising groups, and joint sessions with Women's Liberation groups. "The Gay Liberation Manifesto" by Carl Whittman and "Sexism, Racism and White Faggotry in Sodomist Amerika" by Nick Benton were focal materials.
  - Law Programs. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    This folder contains items regarding legislation relating to gays which Arizona gay groups were interested in; it contains materials from joint GLAD II--ACLU programs dealing with both the Law and law enforcement. Additional materials are in Box 2, 8.
  - Library Projects. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    GLAD II attempted to increase and improve library holdings on homosexuality and gay liberation; to interest gays in the use of materials on these topics; and to provide through its own lending library and the sale of Gay Sunshine alternative gay literature services in cooperation with Southwest Communications Center. More materials in Box 2, 9 and in Box 3, 1.
  - Free University Classes. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    These items show the structure and topics of GLAD II's self-education project, listed through the Free University.
  - Urban Plunge. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    GLAD II participated in a program coordinated by the Campus Christian Center designed to familiarize suburban Tucsonans with local inner-city and minority groups.
  - Stonewall Demonstration. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    On December 2, 1972, GLAD II staged a demonstration protesting the dress code of a Tucson gay bar. Additional comments on such dress codes is in Box 3, 5, Issue 7.
  - Gay Pride Week. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    This material includes notes, materials, and clippings about GLAD II's celebration, April 2-8, 1973
- Series II: Subject Resources
  - Anita Bryant. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Clippings on her anti-gay campaign.
  - Bibliographies. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    This folder includes, among others, the American Library Association, SRRT, and Gay Liberation Task Force bibliographies.
  - Campus Organizations. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Clippings on campus gay liberation organizations outside Arizona.
  - Children. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Clippings on relationships of gay people to children and childcare. Additional material is available in Box 3, 6.
  - Consciousness-Raising. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Articles, guides, and materials dealing with small-group, personal-experience sessions. Box 3, 1 Issue 1 deals with consciousness-raising. See also Box 4, Gay Men's Referral Training Tapes 1 and 2.
  - Effeminism. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Materials used by the Effeminist Study Group including letters from Kenneth Pitchford and Steven Dansky.
  - Gay Community Services Center, Los Angeles. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Brochures and flyers advertising the Center's services. See also box 2, 11, Envelope 3.
  - Heakin Murder. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Newspaper clippings regarding Richard Heakin's murder in Tucson by four teenage boys.
  - Law. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Clippings, handbills, and statutes, all regarding homosexual acts and gay issues. See also Box 1, 10 and Box 2, 19 and 20. Hear Box 4, Gay Men's Referral Training Tape 3.
  - Librarianship. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Notes and copies regarding library service to gay patrons and employment of gay librarians. Related local materials in Box 1, 11 and in Box 3, 1.
  - Matrix Workshop Materials. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    These pamphlets were developed for 1974 Tucson Awareness House workshops and were subsequently used at other places, including Pima College, Tucson, AZ.
  - Medicine Brother, no. 6. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Additional material "Toward a Gay Men's Health Guide" in Box 3, 7. Hear Box 4, Gay Men's Referral Training Tape 2.
    Envelope 1: VD, General Gay Health, Medical Profession
    Envelope 2: Pima County Health Department, hear also Box 4, Gay Men's Referral Training Tape 2
    Envelope 3: Materials from Gay Community Services Center, Los Angeles, Men's Clinic
  - Military. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Material about gays in the military and about the war in Vietnam and related homosexual issues.
  - Minority Status. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    A copy of Franklin Kameny's article "Homosexuals as a Minority Group" and notes; a copy of Mary MacIntosh's article "Homosexual Role." Locally relevant material in Box 3, 1.
  - Music. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Clippings on sexism and popular music.
  - Psychology-Psychiatry. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Clippings and articles about gay clients and professional attitudes toward gays. Additional material in Box 1, 8 and in Box 3, 5, Issue 2.
  - Religion. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Clippings and articles about Christian attitudes toward homosexuals and women.
  - Semmen's Affair. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    ASUA Senator Robert F. Semmen was asked by the Gay Student Organization to resign.
  - Sexual Techniques. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Articles about gay male sexuality.
  - Transvestism. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Materials about homosexual cross-dressing.
  - Travel. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Articles about group travel for gays.
  - Corrie Furst. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Clippings about her being fired for bisexuality by Amphitheater Junior High School and the suit which followed.
  - Marvin Wayne Walden. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Correspondence from Arizona State Prison, Florence, inmate regarding prison reform and gay rights suits.
  - "Word is Out" (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Seminar papers.
  - Miscellaneous Notes of Rick Wilson. (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Series III: Articles authored by Jack Latham, 1973-1975
  - New Times: "VD for Gays, Women" with Colleen Elegante. February 14, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - New Times: "Ya Gotcha Crabs" with Colleen Elegante. August 3, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - New Times: What is a Minority?" April 30, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Worm: "Report from Berkeley." March-April, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Law Wives' Association, A Lecture for the: "Playing the Game by Someone Else's Rules." March 12, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Metropolitan Community Church, A Sermon for the: "Stigma and Community." May 11, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Mountain News Real, Number 1: "CR and Gay Solidarity." No date (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mountain News Real, Number 2: "Gay Heads and Straight Shrinks." June 1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mountain News Real, Number 3: "Gay Directory: Try Tucson First (Gay)." September 1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mountain New Real, Number 4: "True Thoughts for Gay People." October 1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mountain New Real, Number 5: No column. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mountain News Real, Number 6: "Faggots: Butch or Fem?" December 1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mountain News Real, Number 7: "Gay Bars: Denim Threads Among the Gold." February 1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Gay Sunshine, Number 14: "Dear Sunshine: S & M" (Letter to the Editor). February 1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Gay Sunshine, Number 24: "A Faggot Father Speaks Out." Spring 1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Unpublished Materials. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Materials include:
    Information on W. H. Auden
    Notes toward a gay perspective and Arizona history
    "The Beginnings of a Gay Man's Health Guide"
- Series IV: Gay Sunshine Material
  - Correspondence with Gay Sunshine (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Largely regarding GLAD II's sale of Gay Sunshine.
  - Gay Sunshine Index. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Including issues 1-24, plus the only issue of offshoot People's Gay Sunshine.
  - People's Gay Sunshine and Gay Sunshine,1-24. (Box 4, Folder 3-7)
    Issue one is a photocopy.
- Series V: Audio Recordings, 1973-1975
  - Suicide Prevention Center. 1973 (Box 4)
    One reel, two sides, Dandelion Oquitadas and Jack Latham.
  - Gay Men's Referral Training and Consciousness-Raising. 1975 (Box 4)
    Three reels containing three of eight sessions.
    No. 1, side one: Consciousness-Raising, Gay History, and Minority Status featuring Jack Latham
    No. 1, side two: "What I like best and least about being gay."
    No. 2, side one: Gay Men's Health featuring Jack Latham and consciousness-raising group, "VD."
    No. 3, side one: Gay Men and the Law featuring Jack Latham